<?xml-model href="../../schemas/schema_coding_primary_texts.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<document>
    <metadata>
        <archive>
            <name>NLR</name>
            <call>Fond 940 (Kun), no. 144</call>
            <fol>1-2</fol>
        </archive>
        <serial>190</serial>
        <entity>Russia</entity>
        <original type="scan"/>
        <complete type="partial"/>
        <cat_gloss>N/A</cat_gloss>
        <cat_date>N/A</cat_date>
        <gloss>Simple list of books covered in madrasa curriculum, collected by Alexander
            Kun.</gloss>
        <keywords>education madrasa</keywords>
    </metadata>
    <body>
        <!-- Cross-referenced with Sarfraz Khan, Muslim Reformist Political Thought: Revivalists, Modernists and Free Will (Routledge, 2013).-->
        <div type="heading">طریق تحصیل
            <flag type="orthography">پایان</flag>
             بمشکلات</div>
        <div type="line">اینکه اوّلاً
            <intertext>اوّلِ علم
                <!-- Avval-i-Ilm ('Beginning of knowledge') - a book written in Tajiki that covered the most
        essential religious rules in a question-answer form" (Khan, 40). -->
            </intertext>
             بعد از ان
            <intertext>بدان<!-- "(i) The study began with Bidan (know!) - a customary name of an
        anonymous treatise on Arabic grammar, widely used in Central Asia as a textbook. This book
        explained fundamentals of Arabic grammar in Tajiki with examples in Arabic" (Khan, 40). --></intertext>
             را</div>
        
        
        (3) Al-Muizzi: بعد از ان مُعِْزی را ** "(iv) Al-muizzi, an anonymous treatise on Arabic
        morphology attributed to Izzuddin Zanjani (1257) and Avomil al-In'a ('Necessary Factors'),
        written by Abdulqahar Jurjani (d. 1080), that dealt with Arabic syntax were used to learn
        Arabic etymology and syntax. Students memorized Arabic idioms and learnt their meanings in
        Tajiki" (Khan, 40). * (4) بعد از ان نه [بخانی \ نجانی] را **‌ ??? * (5) Awamil: بعد از ان
        عوامل ** Awamil al-Nahw? * (6) Harakat: بعد از ان حرکات را و این مجموع را علم صرف میگویند *
        (7) Qafia: بعد از ان شروع بکافیه میکنند و این مشتمل بر هفت مبحث اولا بحث اسم و ثانیا مرفوعات
        بعد از ان منصوبات و بعد از ان مجرورات و بعد از ان [مبنیات] بعد از ان بحث فعل بعد از ان بحث
        حرف ** "(v) This was followed by a partial reading of Qafia fi-n-nahv ('Rhyme in Grammar') -
        one of the most widely read textbooks on Arabic grammar, written by Ibn al-Hajib (d. 1249).
        The book discussed Arabic syntax in some detail. The study of these books was considered
        sufficient to become a mulla. Sometimes students took up to ten years to complete this
        stage" (Khan, 40). ** //Note misspelling if قافیه in the Kun version.// * (8) Sharh-i Mulla:
        و بعد از ان شروع بشرح ملا میکنند و این شرح کافیه ست ** "The next stage of advanced learning
        began with the reading of Sharh-i-Mulla ('Explanation of mulla'), a commentary written by
        Abdurahman Jami (d. 1492) on Qafia fi-n-nahv" (Khan, 40). * (9) Abd al-Ghafur's grammar: و
        بر بالای شرح ملا ملا عبد الغفور را قراة میکنند و این مجموع را علم نحو میگویند * (10)
        Shamsiyya: و بعد از ان شروع بشمسیه میکنند ** "This stage took five years and included the
        study of Najamuddin Qazvini's (d. 1276) book on logic, Arrisalat ash-Shamsia fi-l-Qavaid
        al-Mantiqia (Treatise on rules of Logic), commonly known as Shamsia" (Khan, 40). * (11)
        Hashiya: و بعد از ان شروع بحاشیه میکنند ** "Students spent another year in reading a
        commentary by Qutbiddin Razi (d. 1365) on Shamsia, known as F. 2 Hoshia-a-Qutbi ('Notes of
        Qutbi')" (40). * (12) بر بالای حاشیه [میر سید / مرشید] شریف و ملا احمد را قراءة میککند ** ??
        * (13) بر بالای مر سید شریف مولوی عبد الحکیم را قراءت میکنند ** ?? * (14) بر بالای ملا عبد
        الحکیم قل احمد را قراءت میکنند ** ?? * (continuing from 14??): و این شرح شمسیه است و این را
        علم منطق میگویند * (15) Aqa'id: و بعد از ان شروع بعقاید میکنند ** "Simultaneously, students
        studied Aqaid-i-Nasafi ('Beliefs of Nasafi'), a theological compilation by Najmuddin Abu
        Hafs Nasafi (1068-1148)" (Khan, 40). * (16) و بر بالای عقاید مولوی خیالی و مولوی عبد الحکیم
        و مولوی احمد را قرأة میکنند ** ??? * (17) Tahzib: و بعد از ان شروع بر [سر تاج؟] تهذیب میکنند
        ** "Tahzib ul-Mantiq va-l-Kalam ('Refinement of Logic and Kalam'), a compilation of logic
        and theology written by Taftazani was studied for two years" (Khan, 40). * (18) و بر بالای
        تهذیب مولوی خاجه جمال و آخوند و میرزا زاهد جان و قاضی مبارک شاه را قراء میکنند ** ??? * (19)
        Hikmat al-Ayn: و بعد از ان شروع بحکمة العین میکنند ** "and then [after Tahzib] Hikmat-ul-Ain
        ('Exact Wisdom') written by Najamuddin Qazvini, dealing with natural history and
        metaphysics, was studied for two more years" (Khan, 40). * (20) و بر بالای حکمة العین میر
        سید شریف و اخوند و میرزا جان را قراة میکنند ** ??? - same as above * (21) Mulla Jalal: و بعد
        از ان شروع بملا جلال میکنند ** ""For another two years students learned Mulla Jalal - a
        commentary written by Jalal-ud-Din Dawwani (d. 1502) on a theological treatise called Aqaid
        ul-Adudiyat ('Beliefs of Adud') by Adud ad-Din al-Iji (d. 1326)" (Khan, 40-41). * (22) و بر
        بالای ملا جلال اخوند خانقای و تتمه را قراء میکنند ** ??? * (23) و بعد از ان شروع بتوضیح
        میککند ** ??? * (24) و بر بالای توضیح تلویح را قرأء میکنند ** ??? * (25) و بعد از ان شروع
        بمشکاة ** ??? * (26) Tafsir: و بعد از ان بتفسیر میکنند * Graduation: و بعد از ان ان از
        استادان فاتحه میگیرند </body>
</document>
